<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon at the funeral of Sir John Norton, Bar. lately deceased prech'd at the Parish-Church of East-Tysted in Hantshire by Thomas Mannyngham.</title>
            <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30510</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11343105</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11343105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47526</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51816)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1465:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon at the funeral of Sir John Norton, Bar. lately deceased prech'd at the Parish-Church of East-Tysted in Hantshire by Thomas Mannyngham.</title>
                  <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Norton, John, --  Sir, 1620?-1687.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Biography.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47526:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47526:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON AT THE FUNERAL OF Sir <hi>JOHN NORTON,</hi> Bar. Lately deceaſed.</p>
            <p>Preach'd in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Eaſt-Tyſted</hi> in <hi>HANTSHIRE:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Mannyngham,</hi> Rector of that Pariſh, and Preacher at the <hi>Rolls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:47526:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hen. Maurice</hi> R. P. D. <hi>Wilhelmo,</hi> Archiepiſc. Cant. a Sacris.</p>
            <p>Feb. 7. 1687.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47526:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:47526:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47526:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the much Honoured Lady, THE Lady <hi>DOROTHY NORTON, Relict</hi> of Sir JOHN NORTON Lately deceas'd.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was my Propoſal, that if there were any thing acceptable in <hi>this Sermon,</hi> Your <hi>Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> might have it firſt tranſcrib'd for your own uſe, and in that manner communicate it to what Friends <hi>You</hi> pleas'd. But ſince <hi>Your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> is of another Judgment, as that
<pb facs="tcp:47526:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>one,</hi> who was every way ſo <hi>worthy,</hi> and ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally <hi>known</hi> and <hi>belov'd,</hi> deſerves to be made <hi>more publick,</hi> I humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. Only I have one thing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that if at any time I ſhould be accuſed of <hi>Flattery</hi> in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>this Subject</hi> (and if I ſhould, it can be by ſuch Perſons only, as envy all Commendations that are given to others, or were very igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Worth of <hi>Sir John Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>) Your Ladyſhip would be ready to vindicate me from that <hi>Aſperſion;</hi> and to witneſs, that as my <hi>Paſtoral Behaviour</hi> towards my <hi>Honoured Patron,</hi> both in the time of his <hi>Health,</hi> and of his <hi>Illneſs,</hi> had never <hi>that Guilt</hi> upon it; ſo now likewiſe, though it be leſs dangerous, I have
<pb facs="tcp:47526:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>not beſtowed upon <hi>Him</hi> any unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Praiſe: But though ſome parts of <hi>His Character</hi> may ſeem warmly, and very affectionately repreſented, yet there are none of them <hi>above</hi> the Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> I ſhall not here attempt any <hi>Conſolatory Diſcourſe;</hi> neither ſhall I undertake, either to <hi>deſcribe,</hi> or to <hi>renew Your Grief;</hi> but I ſhall rather chuſe to draw a <hi>Vail</hi> over it at preſent, or leave <hi>You</hi> to declare it <hi>Yourſelf;</hi> not by fruitleſs Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and dark Retirements, as if <hi>You</hi> were diſcontented at Providence and the World, but (what is a clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Argument of Your <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and Your <hi>Love,</hi>) <hi>by doing all things in Honour of the deceaſed, the whole remainder of Your days.</hi> And as <hi>You</hi> have hitherto been, not only a
<pb facs="tcp:47526:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Companion</hi> with <hi>Him</hi> in all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable Actions, but an <hi>Encourager</hi> too; ſo I doubt not, but <hi>Your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> will continue the <hi>ſame Acts</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> keep up the <hi>ſame decent Hoſpitality,</hi> improve the <hi>ſame Friendſhips,</hi> reſpect the <hi>Clergy</hi> which <hi>He</hi> ſo truly lov'd, maintain the <hi>ſame Conſtancy</hi> in attending on the <hi>publick Worſhip</hi> of God, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the <hi>ſame Faith:</hi> Then the Almighty will bleſs <hi>Your Ladyſhip</hi> with the <hi>Proſperity</hi> of this Life, and afterwards admit <hi>You</hi> to the <hi>ſame Place</hi> of Joy and Reſt, whither Your <hi>Deareſt Husband</hi> is gone before. Which that he may do, is the hearty Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Faithful, and moſt Obedient Servant,</hi> Tho. Mannyngham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47526:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM XV. v. 1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Lord, who ſhall abide in thy Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle? who ſhall dwell in thy holy Hill?</p>
                  <p>He that walketh uprightly, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Righteouſneſs, and ſpeaketh the truth in his Heart.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS <hi>Pſalm</hi> may be called a Deſcription of a <hi>Citizen of Sion,</hi> of one that God will admit unto all the Priviledges of his Sanctuary here, and reward with eternal Happineſs hereafter. For whoſoever ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders his Converſation in this World, as to live and die a true Member of the Church of God, ſhall never fall, ſhall never be moved, but ſhall ſtand in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the righteous for ever: Or, though
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47526:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>in ſome ſenſe, he fall by Death, yet ſhall he riſe again by a glorious Reſurrection; tho' he be moved, yet it is but from one Church to another, from the Church Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant to the Church Triumphant.</p>
            <p>In the Words we have a moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Queſtion propoſed by the Prophet <hi>David</hi> to God himſelf; <hi>Lord, who ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in thy Tabernacle? who ſhall dwell in thy holy Hill?</hi> and God preſently returns an Anſwer, as it were, by a voice out of the Clouds; He <hi>that walketh uprightly, and worketh Righteouſneſs, and ſpeaketh the truth in his Heart:</hi> Theſe being the chief diſtinguiſhing Marks of a true <hi>Iſraelite;</hi> for whatever Particulars are contained in the following part of this Pſalm, may be reduced to theſe general Heads, of <hi>Integrity, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here therefore we ſee what are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and ſubſtantial things that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires to fit us for his Communion, and ſo make us capable of the peculiar Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of his Covenant and Promiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch Moral Duties, as evidence the Truth and Simplicity of our Hearts, and declare
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47526:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Uprightneſs of our Converſation with Men; for by theſe he meaſures the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of all thoſe who come to worſhip him.</p>
            <p>Nothing was more liable to the abuſes of Hypocriſie, than the Ceremonial or Tabernacle Service of the <hi>Jews,</hi> (which is proportionably true of all other outward Worſhip whatever) and therefore God tries the Truth of their moſt ſolemn Acts of Worſhip, by their Conformity to the plaineſt Duties of Human Society: For <hi>what does the Lord require of thee,</hi> ſaies the Prophet <hi>Micha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>but to do juſtly, and to love Mercy, and to walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy God?</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> tells them,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.17, 18.</note> that the <hi>Kingdom of God conſiſts in Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt. For he that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approved of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not my Buſineſs at preſent to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon any Point of Divinity, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to declare what are the Qualifications which the Prophet <hi>David</hi> here gives of his <hi>true Citizen of Sion,</hi> and then to conſider
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47526:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>how near a Reſemblance, the Life of the <hi>Honourable Perſon,</hi> whoſe Funeral Rites we are now performing, had to the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laid down in this Pſalm: So that when we ſhall find <hi>Him</hi> to have maintain'd a great <hi>Integrity, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> through the whole Courſe of his days, and alſo to have been a conſtant and devout <hi>Worſhipper</hi> of God in his holy Tabernacle, we may have good Chriſtian Hope, and Comfort, and Confidence to conclude, that he is now praiſing and glorifying the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in a more excellent manner in the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Therefore I ſhall endeavour to make it evident, that in the main Actions of his Life, <hi>He</hi> duly practis'd the great Moral and Political Duties laid down in this Pſalm, both as a private Perſon, and as a publick Magiſtrate.</item>
               <item>II. That, as in Conformity to the Rules of this Pſalm, <hi>He</hi> was rightly qualified to abide in the holy Tabernacle, ſo accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly he liv'd and dy'd a devout <hi>Worſhipper</hi> of God. And therefore,</item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:47526:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>III. We have reaſon to conclude, that his Soul is now at reſt upon the ſpiritual <hi>Sion,</hi> the holy Mount of God.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. I ſhall endeavour to make it evident, That in the main Actions of his Life, <hi>He</hi> duly practis'd the great Moral and Political Duties laid down in this Pſalm, both as a private Perſon, and as a publick Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed to <hi>his Character,</hi> it may be worth our Obſervation to conſider what a proper Place and Eſteem the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> has given theſe Vertues of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> by making <hi>them</hi> the chief Ingredients whenever he deſcribes a truly pious Man: So that let the Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Peace and Truth, contend never ſo earneſtly about Opinions, Speculations, and outward ways of Worſhip, Men are no further religious, than they are honeſt and juſt: Our practiſing the Duties of the ſecond Table, being the beſt Evidence that we can give of our right Obſervation of the Duties of the firſt; as may be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47526:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>manifeſted through the whole Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the Old and New Teſtament; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, through all the account of the Lives of the Patriarchs, through the ancient Book of <hi>Job,</hi> the Pſalms of <hi>David,</hi> the Proverbs of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Sermons of the Prophets, the Expoſitions, Parables, and Diſcourſes of our Saviour, and the Rules and Precepts of the Apoſtles: And they who forſake theſe plain, and numerous, and divine Teſtimonies of what was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways eſteemed <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>ſincere Religion,</hi> and undertake to dreſs <hi>it</hi> up in new No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their own, as they beſt ſuit with their private Paſſions, Fancies, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Intereſts, may make Mankind either ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Worſhippers of they know not <hi>what,</hi> or phantaſtically zealous they know not <hi>why;</hi> but will never perſwade People to be truly humble, charitable, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially Good; or imprint upon their Minds an awful and juſt Reverence of the Eternal and Incomprehenſible Godhead. Now the <hi>Honourable Perſon,</hi> whoſe bodily Remains are here before us, was one who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47526:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhew'd the Truth of his Religion, by the Honeſty and Juſtice of his Life; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd his Faith in God, by his Fidelity to Man. He never took up a Reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Neighbour, or a Reward againſt the Innocent, or admitted of any unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Gain; but was true to all his Covenants and Contracts, faithfully kept his Oath of Allegiance, and would ſtill have done ſo, tho' it had been to his temporal Hindrance.</p>
            <p>All <hi>you</hi> who are now preſent, can ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifie his exceeding Worth in all the Variety of his Capacities and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, both private and publick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You</hi> who are of the <hi>Nobility, Gentry,</hi> and <hi>his worthy Relations,</hi> can witneſs the high Generoſity of his Soul, the Greatneſs and Conſtancy of his Friendſhips, the Love, the Honour, and the Sincerity of all his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You</hi> can witneſs, (for many of <hi>You</hi> were Partners with Him in all his eminent Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and deſerve your Commendations too) <hi>You</hi> can witneſs how aſſiduous and punctual He was in all the Important
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47526:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Truſts that were committed to Him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Auguſt Aſſembly of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> his honourable Commands in the <hi>Militia,</hi> or his Juſtitiary Affairs upon the <hi>Bench.</hi> How highly Loyal He was ever to His King, and yet a ſtudious Preſerver of the ancient Priviledges of his Countrey; but yet no ſuch turbulent Lover of his Countrey, as any ways to undermine the juſt Prerogatives of the Crown. How firm and reſolute He always was for upholding the eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>England,</hi> and yet not Factious againſt the right Succeſſion. How vaſt an Empire he had obtained in the Affections of the People by his Affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, his Hoſpitality, and his repeated Acts of Kindneſs; and yet how innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how juſtly, and how loyally He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged ſo dangerous a Power. That large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extended <hi>Popularity</hi> in which he always liv'd, and which would have made perhaps another man vainly giddy, or ſeditious, made him more thoughtful, and more ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the Crown. For he could not but conſider what peculiar Obligations He had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47526:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be faithful to the Government, ſince ſo great a Multitude of all ſorts had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelves to his charge, and own'd Him for their Oracle in Civil Wiſdom. Therefore He guided them in all humble Submiſſion to their Sovereign, and inſpir'd them with that Allegiance, which He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly practis'd himſelf; which he practis'd with the ſame Sincerity, with the ſame Conſcience of his Oath to God, as well as to Man, under all Accidents and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, through all Variations and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; for no Sufferings could terrifie Him, no Proſperity could ſoften him out of his Duty; no publick Diſcontents could ſowre Him, no private Friendſhips could byaſs Him: But lo! He has now concluded the <hi>Male-Line</hi> of his Loyal Anceſtors with untainted Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and may all his collateral Poſterity both imitate and inherit the Glory of this his Character! And may all <hi>You,</hi> who were his Noble Friends and Acquaintance, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ſame illuſtrious, as well as truly Chriſtian Vertue, to the end of your days; whatever difficulties ariſe, whatever tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Loſſes <hi>You</hi> undergo; for otherwiſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47526:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>You</hi> will blaſt the Reputation of the Church of <hi>England, You</hi> will forfeit the Protection of the Divine Providence, and loſe the faireſt Opportunity that this Nation ever had of glorifying God, by a meek perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in Obedience and Truth. And as <hi>You</hi> are Chriſtians, you muſt acknowledge, that the Goſpel is not upheld by Wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but by Humility, and by Patience.</p>
            <p>They who are of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> can teſtifie what Regard he always paid to <hi>that Order,</hi> how gladly he receiv'd their Viſits, many times return'd them, and never ſeem'd more ſatisfy'd than when his Table was fill'd with their Society. He was not afraid of their Learning, their Prudence, and their Obſervations, but could throughly reliſh their wiſeſt Diſcourſes, and match their accuteſt Sayings.</p>
            <p>A Reverend and a Virtuous Divine was no tedious Burden to him, no Cenſure on his Manners, no Comedy to his Servants, and no Jeſt among his Family: No, I am ſure, whoever of them brought any Eſteem along with them to his Houſe, never went
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47526:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>away with it any ways diminiſh'd, but rather increas'd with the Additions of a due Reſpect.</p>
            <p>He well knew the ſad Degeneracy of this Age, with what Contempt and Scorn the Men of that Function are many times treated by thoſe, who envy their Subſiſtence, and hate their Vertues; who having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd their Allegiance to God, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually offering Violence to his Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and being conſcious to themſelves, that they have juſtly deſerv'd an Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication for the notorious lewdneſs of their Lives, cannot but expect an <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> from every Church-man that they meet, and therefore treat them as their greateſt Enemies.</p>
            <p>Theſe horrible Impieties he knew were too much in faſhion among the Great, in whom Civility and common Manners are uſually accounted the loweſt of their Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, and therefore he endeavour'd to ſet them a better Example, for he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any thing to do with the Throne of Wickedneſs, or with the Chair of the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47526:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>He never put thoſe Faces to Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that were made tender by Modeſty and Retirement; he never caſt a Cloud of Infamy and Reproach upon the Beauty of Holineſs; but he always rejoyc'd to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his Reverence of God, and his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to Religion, by his proportionable Reſpects to the Clergy; he lov'd to be a Partaker of the Tranquility, the Wiſdom, the innocent and meek Converſation, the Joy and Gladneſs of the Righteous, and to be held a Companion of all thoſe, who with an unparalell'd,<note place="margin">John 15.14, 15.</note> but yet unenvy'd Title, are call'd the <hi>Friends</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thus he fully anſwer'd that part of the Character of a <hi>Citizen of Sion,</hi> laid down in this Pſalm, where it is ſaid of him, That <hi>in his Eyes a vile Perſon is contemned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 4.</note> 
               <hi>but he honoureth them that fear the Lord.</hi> Indeed his Civility embrac'd all men, though his Judgment knew well how to diſtinguiſh: To contemn any one, was not in his Nature, though it ſometimes happen'd to be his Duty, eſpecially as a Magiſtrate. But the <hi>vile Perſons</hi> that he contemn'd, were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47526:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>not the poor and deſtitute, thoſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd: They were not thoſe of a mean or common Parentage, for ſuch he many times enobled with his Invitations and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Notice; neither were they thoſe, whoſe Vices were private, or known only by common rumour, or long ſince com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; for as to ſuch things he was not haſty to judge any, but left them to God, and their own Conſciences, deſpiſing none as <hi>Publicans,</hi> becauſe he could not tell what <hi>Saints</hi> Repentance might one day make them. But the <hi>vile Perſons</hi> that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd, were more eſpecially the buſie Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of Church and State, either by open Rebellion, ſecret Conſpiracy, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellous Pamphlets: And likewiſe among the <hi>vile Perſons,</hi> he could not but reckon all ſuch (though otherwiſe never ſo high in Quality) who ſcoff'd at Religion, and deſpis'd the Clergy; becauſe ſo profligate a Demeanour towards ſacred things and perſons, was an Argument to him of the worſt of Tempers that was incident to human Nature, as denoting both the higheſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47526:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>pitch of <hi>Prophaneneſs,</hi> and the loweſt Dregs of <hi>Senſuality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our good <hi>Citizen of Sion</hi> made much of them that feared the Lord, defended them from the Inſolence of thoſe that would oppreſs them, render'd them Awe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their Flocks and Charges, teaching <hi>them</hi> new meaſures of Reverence by his own Demeanour, making them ready and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to render their whole Dues, when they ſaw him, who was ſo ſtrict an Obſerver of Judgment, Mercy and Truth, to be ſo exact and punctual in the payment of all his <hi>Tythes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had no Fortunes to make, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digally waſted Patrimony to repair by Fraud and Sacriledge, but what was wanting to the ancient Demeſns of his worthy Family, was nobly loſt by their faithful adherence to the Church and Crown, and therefore never to be re-built upon <hi>their Ruines:</hi> Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the loſs <hi>it</hi> underwent in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Wars, <hi>it</hi> ſtill remain'd an ample, and a thriving Eſtate under the Diſcretion and <hi>Liberality</hi> of its Owner; it had no Canker
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47526:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>in it, no unjuſt Titles to moulder it away, no Curſe of the Needy upon it, but was alway bleſſed with the good Providence of God, the Prayers of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and of the Poor. And thus ſhall every Man be bleſſed that maketh much of them that fear the Lord. They that love God's Miniſters, ſhall be beloved of God; they ſhall dwell in plenty all their days, deſcend with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour unto their Graves, and their Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhall be dear and ſacred, as long as Learning, and Wiſdom, and Piety ſhall remain.</p>
            <p>They who are of the <hi>Commonalty</hi> can ſufficiently witneſs the Condeſcentions of his Kindneſs, the eaſie Familiarity of his Converſe, the readineſs of his Favours, and the uprightneſs of his Magiſtracy; how he us'd his Authority chiefly to reconcile the minds of thoſe that were offended with each other, to cool their Paſſions, to leſſen their Differences, to recommend the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Peace and Amity, to declare the ill Conſequences of Enmity and Revenge, and by threatning the Rigour of the Laws, to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47526:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>keep them from the puniſhments of them.</p>
            <p>How often have fierce and contending Adverſaries forgot their Malice in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and been aſham'd to proſecute their Neighbours before him, who always was ſo kind to his? He was every way ſo compleatly fitted for his <hi>Juſtitiary Jmploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> by his Wiſdom, his Equity, and his Reputation, that there were few but were ready to ſtand to whatever he propos'd: They were fully poſſeſs'd with an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his perſon, and his worth; they knew how inflexible he was in Honeſty and Truth, and repair'd to him, rather as an Arbitrator, than as a Magiſtrate; and accordingly he manag'd their Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, as a true Lover of his Countrey, and an equal Guardian of Peace and Concord; he often ſerv'd the true ends of Government more by adviſing as a Friend, than by giving out Orders as a <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd more Differences by the good hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of a Gentleman, than by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a Magiſtrate.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:47526:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>You can witneſs how he ſpent his time and his Eſtate continually in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and ſcarce ever went to <hi>London,</hi> but to attend in the Parliaments, and there to promote <hi>your Intereſt;</hi> how he preferr'd his Habitation here, before all the Splendor and Diverſions of the City; and how he valued the plain and downright Affection of honeſt and induſtrious Farmers, before the fineſt Profeſſions of Flattery and Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; you cannot but remember with what chearfulneſs of Looks, and heartineſs of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, he receiv'd you to his Table, which you always found loaded with ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Proviſions, as having ſerv'd the Parlour, afterwards feaſted the Hall, and plentifully reliev'd the Poor at his Gates.</p>
            <p>When his Houſe was fill'd (as it often was) with promiſcuous Gueſts, how ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligingly would he accommodate himſelf to Perſons of all degrees and ranks; ſalute the <hi>Gentry</hi> with compleat Addreſs; give ſuch reſpect unto the <hi>Clergy,</hi> as ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite others to pay the ſame; talk friendly and facetiouſly with the <hi>middle</hi> ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47526:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>kindly and affably with the <hi>Loweſt:</hi> Nay, he would oftentimes give Life and Countenance to the <hi>meaneſt Gueſts,</hi> by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Applications, and the repeated Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of their Welcome.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who were his <hi>Tenants,</hi> can witneſs how far he was from being a <hi>hard Landlord,</hi> or requiring more than his Ground would yield; how favourably he conſider'd all Caſualties, how deſirous he was of their honeſt Profit, what Pleaſure he took in ſeeing them proſper and thrive! ſo that we may be aſſur'd,<note place="margin">Job 31.38.</note> that his <hi>Land will never cry againſt him, nor the Furrows thereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Servants</hi> know what a gracious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter they have loſt, in whoſe Service they found no harſhneſs of Commands, and no Indulgence unto Vice: To retain unto him, was not Licentiouſneſs, but Diſcipline and good Manners; neither was it Slavery, but Preferment; and accordingly they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd their Duty more from Love, than from Fear.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:47526:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Some he educated and provided for, with the tenderneſs of a Father, ſome he apprentis'd out to profitable and honeſt Callings; he rewarded all that any ways deſerv'd, and there were few but did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; for he took care to inſtill both Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Religion into them, and to let them know, that he was moſt offended, when they neglected their Duty to God: He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver affected much Appearance or Splendor in his <hi>Retinue;</hi> but the only <hi>Pomp</hi> in which he ſeem'd to be moſt delighted, was in walking conſtantly to the Houſe of God, before a numerous and well-order'd Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
            <p>And now, Beloved, you may think perhaps that I have finiſh'd his Character by theſe ſeveral Appeals, which I have made to thoſe who fully underſtood his multiply'd Worth; but yet there <hi>are greater things</hi> behind for <hi>my ſelf</hi> to witneſs, which will ſhew him to have been a <hi>devout Worſhipper of God;</hi> and that theſe ſundry Inſtances of his <hi>Integrity, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> which I have already given, were but either ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47526:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>many preparatory Qualifications to, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative Evidences of, the <hi>Reality</hi> of his <hi>Devotions:</hi> For without ſome Degree of theſe, Men are not fit for the <hi>ſolemn Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of God; and without an Improvement in theſe, their Worſhip is but Mockery and Prophaneneſs: To be <hi>Honeſt, Juſt,</hi> and <hi>Faithful,</hi> or, what is all one, <hi>to be without Guile,</hi> is perhaps the <hi>ſafeſt Deſcription</hi> of a good Chriſtian, that the New Teſtament affords us; our Saviour gave it of <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> when he call'd him an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed, <hi>John</hi> 1.47. Nay, it is given of our bleſſed Saviour himſelf, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Who did no Sin, neither was Guile found in his Mouth.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.5. it is there affirm'd of thoſe who are repreſented as the higheſt Order of Saints in the Reſurrection, that <hi>in their Mouth was found no Guile.</hi> Without this ſure and ſtanding Evidence of the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of <hi>the Heart,</hi> we may be at ſtrange Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties about our judging and defining what is true <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Vertue;</hi> for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience has aſſur'd us, that Men may have ſuch odd Apprehenſions of the <hi>Divinity</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:47526:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>they worſhip, as may root out all their Remains of <hi>Moral Honeſty;</hi> and things may arrive to that deſperate Paſs, that ſome Mens <hi>Piety</hi> ſhall be nothing but an <hi>Extaſie</hi> about <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Ranckneſs</hi> of <hi>Self-love</hi> under the ſacred name of <hi>Zeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having, therefore, atteſted the <hi>Integrity, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> of this Great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar before us, and finding him ſo well qualify'd, according to the Method of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> to be a <hi>Worſhipper of God,</hi> I ſhall in the</p>
            <p>Second place conſider how he behav'd himſelf in that ſpiritual Priviledge and Station.</p>
            <p>He was admirably compos'd by the <hi>ſincerity</hi> of his Temper, and the <hi>ſeriouſneſs</hi> of his Affections, for the <hi>ſolemn Worſhip</hi> of God; he ſeem'd to me to have an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſenſe of the Majeſty of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Mind, a deep and unaffected Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in all his Thoughts, and religious Actions; and ſuch a grateful Experience of the Mercies of God, as was always ready to overflow into Praiſes and Thankſgivings.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47526:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>And this <hi>Reverential Habit</hi> of his Soul, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a due mixture of <hi>Fear,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>holy Admiration,</hi> was owing, next to the Grace of God, to that ſtrict, and truly Chriſtian <hi>Education,</hi> which he receiv'd from the Care of his <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>vertuous Parents;</hi> for it was then, that he imbib'd thoſe early and laſting Impreſſions of the <hi>Aweful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Religion,</hi> which he kept inviolate in the <hi>Univerſity,</hi> and in the <hi>Countrey,</hi> which he carried with him from his Youth to his Grave, through all the <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> of the Uſurpation, and through all the <hi>Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> ſince. Nothing was more odious to him, than ſporting with ſacred Things; not, that he wanted a Talent to have fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd out the Wit, but he had a <hi>devout Nature</hi> that abhorr'd the Crime. No Man was more <hi>facetious</hi> than he, when it was ſeaſonable and innocent, but then God and and the holy Scriptures were never any of his Subjects: He was never known to uſe any manner of Jeſting to the Prejudice or Reproach of his Neighbour, and we may be ſure he was much more tender of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his God.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:47526:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>He was ſo far from entertaining any pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Exceptions againſt the excellent <hi>Liturgy</hi> of our Church, that he could never ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admire the <hi>Purity,</hi> the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> the Divine <hi>Plainneſs,</hi> and the compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of our <hi>publick Prayers:</hi> He frequented them, and lov'd them, becauſe he truly reliſh'd them; he truly reliſh'd them, becauſe he came prepar'd unto them, by the <hi>private Devotions</hi> of his Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, which he likewiſe ſuſtain'd and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd by his duly reading, and meditating on the appointed <hi>Pſalms</hi> and <hi>Chapters</hi> for every Morning and Evening throughout the Year.</p>
            <p>His grave and examplary Behaviour in this place, always ſhew'd what an intire Affection he bare to the <hi>whole Service</hi> of the Church; for by his humble Geſtures, his devout and audible Reſponſes, and his exact Conformity to all the outward <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency preſcrib'd,</hi> he was, in a manner, a <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Rubrick</hi> to the whole Congregation; and by his continual and hearty <hi>Amens</hi> to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47526:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>every Prayer, he animated the Devotions of all that were preſent</p>
            <p>He was not one who expected <hi>Curioſities</hi> from the Pulpit, or that the common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or thoſe of an ordinary Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhould be neglected, to ſupply Dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for his Ear: For though he was a Judge of the Purity of Eloquence, the choice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Expreſſion, the clearneſs of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, the ſtrength of an Argument, the depth of ſound Divinity, and the height of an affectionate Piety; yet he was a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer of the plaineſt, and moſt inartifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Inſtructions: Nay, he did not diſdain (as many Great Perſons do) to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Auditor of the repeated Rudiments of Chriſtianity, and the moſt familiar <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing</hi> of the Children; for he well knew, that thoſe <hi>Fundamental Articles</hi> were the important Truths on which our <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> does depend; and that however a <hi>ſufficient Knowledge</hi> of them, may be ſoon acquir'd, even by the meaneſt, humble, and willing Diſciple of Chriſt, yet they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47526:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>contain'd ſuch boundleſs Treaſures of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Senſe and Meaning, as might exerciſe the vaſteſt parts, and continually inrich the moſt improved Mind.</p>
            <p>He was a ſtrict Obſerver of the <hi>Lent</hi> for three days in a Week: He conſtantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the <hi>Holy Sacrament</hi> at the three great Feſtivals of the Year, and ſometimes oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and before every receiving, he uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly injoyn'd himſelf three or four days of <hi>ſtrict Preparation,</hi> and ſometimes more.</p>
            <p>The laſt Sacrament I gave him, which was on <hi>Chriſtmas-day</hi> in his Chamber, it was ſome ſcruple upon him, that he had not prepar'd himſelf more <hi>ſolemnly,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his wonted Method: But when I told him, that I did not doubt, but his extream Pains, and his commendable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience under them, had ſupply'd the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of his former Self-denials, and had wrought him into an humble and heavenly Temper; He reſign'd himſelf to my Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and receiv'd his <hi>Viaticum,</hi> his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Strength, upon His weak and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47526:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Knees. During all His Illneſs, till he kept his Bed, he would not hearken to thoſe that propos'd to him any other <hi>Poſture</hi> in his Prayers; and in the latter part of his Weakneſs, he was pray'd for in many of the neighbouring Churches, in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and in the Chappel of his Dioceſan.</p>
            <p>Thus he was a <hi>true Son</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> follow'd all Her Rites and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, pay'd a ſtrict Obedience to all Her Directions; mourn'd when ſhe ſuffer'd, rejoyc'd when ſhe flouriſh'd, pray'd fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and acted vigorouſly for Her Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, cheriſh'd, reſpected, reverenc'd all Orders of Men within Her; was intimate with a long Succeſſion of Her moſt <hi>eminent Prelates</hi> and <hi>Paſtors;</hi> was greatly honour'd, and intirely lov'd by moſt of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers</hi> that now adorn her, and protect her, by their <hi>Learning,</hi> their <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> their <hi>Fortitude,</hi> and their <hi>Piety.</hi> He was ſo well grounded a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47526:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>no Art or Cunning, no Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, no Terrors, no Loſſes, could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have mov'd him from the two main Pillars of his conſtant <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> viz. his <hi>Duty</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> and his <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>King;</hi> but upon all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, as formerly, ſo ſtill, he would have bravely ſerv'd his Prince to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Extent of what is lawful; and had there been more than this requir'd, he would have humbly and mildly ſuffered for the Teſtimony of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>After a continued Enjoyment of his Health for threeſcore and four years, God was pleaſed to exerciſe him with a ſevere Sickneſs, above two years ſince; from which in ſome time he recovered, though perhaps never to the Strength and Conſiſtency of his former State, yet to a greater Watchfulneſs over all his Actions, and I am perſwaded, to a much further Advancement in his ſpiritual and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Affairs.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:47526:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>About four Months ſince, he was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with an unuſual <hi>Swelling</hi> in the Neck, which at firſt was not apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be of much Conſequence; but the extraordinary Concern of his moſt <hi>Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate Lady,</hi> would not permit her to entertain the like Thoughts; ſhe was reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs between Love and Care, and her Breaſt was filled with melancholy and aloding Fears; the longer it continued, the more confirm'd ſhe was, that there was ſtill ſome <hi>lurking Malignity</hi> in it, not yet diſcovered; and the Event ſhew'd, that ſhe was not miſtaken; for after moſt acute and lingring Pains, through the pungency of the Humour inclos'd, and the Cauſticks that were apply'd, (all which he underwent with wonderful Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Reſignation, never murmuring or repining, but often lifting up his Hands and Eyes in ſilent Prayer) it came at laſt to a <hi>cancerous Ulcer,</hi> through which the whole ſubſtance of his Body was drein'd, notwithſtanding all the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47526:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>of able Phyſicians, all the Skill and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curacy of Expert Surgeons. But though he gradually decayed, and was by many given over, yet ſtill no poſſible means were left unattempted (through the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied Induſtry and Sollicitude, the wiſe, the tender, and the honourable Care of his afflicted and ſorrowful <hi>Lady</hi>) either for his preſent Eaſe and Support, or for his future Recovery; nothing was left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attempted, till the Evening before he died; and then, having a <hi>clear Proſpect</hi> of his approaching End, he told thoſe about him, that he would take nothing more, took his laſt Farewel of his <hi>Dear Wife,</hi> prayed God to bleſs her, and compos'd himſelf for another Life; and the next day, being <hi>Sunday,</hi> between four and five in the Afternoon, without any Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or any Pangs of Death, he calmly reſign'd his Breath, and fell aſleep in the Lord. And this he did in the midſt of the <hi>Commendatory Prayers</hi> and Ejaculations of thoſe who were about him, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47526:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>with his own Miniſter then preſent, who, notwithſtanding his unſought-for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, had the Opportunity of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his noble and beloved Patron, the laſt ſix Weeks of his Illneſs; paſſionately inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding for the acceptance of his Faith and Repentance, through the alone Merits of Chriſt our Saviour; and at the Point of his Departure, humbly preſenting his Spirit unto God.</p>
            <p n="3">III. And now laſtly, what remains, but to comfort one another, that through the Mercies and Forgiveneſſes of our moſt Gracious God (who delights to magnifie himſelf in the Salvation of Mankind) our <hi>Noble Friend,</hi> and <hi>Deareſt Brother,</hi> is now in the Poſſeſſion of <hi>that State of Happineſs,</hi> which the <hi>Souls</hi> of <hi>humble Penitents</hi> receive after this Life; that He is now joyning in the <hi>Hallilujahs</hi> of that Church, which is ſeated above all the Storms and Confuſions of this World; where <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> have no <hi>Diſguiſes,</hi> and where <hi>Religion</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes no <hi>Contentions,</hi> but thoſe of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47526:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Love.</hi> There let us leave his Soul at reſt, and commit his Body to the Earth, till the Reſurrection of the Juſt; and in the mean time, whilſt we have Health and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, let <hi>Us</hi> alſo endeavour to be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in <hi>Integrity, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Fidelity,</hi> in ſpeaking of the Truth, and in doing good; let us maintain the <hi>ſame Loyalty</hi> that he practiſed, pay our conſtant Attendance on the <hi>ſame publick Worſhip</hi> that he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, and die in the <hi>ſame Faith,</hi> in which he died: Then we alſo ſhall one day reſt with him upon the ſame <hi>Spiritual Sion,</hi> the holy Mount of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which God of his infinite Mercy grant, through the alone Merits of Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THere are Five Sermons and Two Diſcourſes by the ſame Author, printed for <hi>William Crooke.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
